A Guide to the Records of the Virginia Secretary of Public Safety, 1976-1982 (bulk 1980-1981)
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Records of the Virginia Secretary of Public Safety, 1976-1982 (bulk 1980-1981)
The Library of Virginia
31662
6 cubic feet (6 boxes)
Virginia Secretary of Public Safety
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Privacy protected and other protected information is considered confidential and restricted from public access for 75 years. It may be necessary for an archivist to review any unprocessed, modern record collections (those collections less than 75 years old) that may contain confidential information before the records can be used by patrons for research purposes or before any copies of records can be made for patrons. If you are planning to use these records, please contact Archives Reference Services for more details before planning your research trip.
If a request for copies is made for material containing confidential information, it is understood that this information will be redacted from the copies, if it is possible to do so. If redaction is not possible, the records will be withheld. Researchers must also agree that no direct or indirect contact will be made with the individuals to whom any personal or confidential information relates. Improper use and/or re-disclosure of privacy protected information is a breach of confidentiality which could result in the loss of access to the archival collections housed and maintained by The Library of Virginia, and could result in legal penalties (Code of Virginia, 18.2-186.3).
Acquisition Information
Transferred by Audrey B. Burton, Office of the Secretary of Public Safety, Ninth Street Office Building, Richmond, Va., 21 January 1983.
Historical Information
In 1970, the Governor's Management Commission Study recommended the creation of six "Deputy Governors" to assist the Chief Executive in his managerial duties. Compatible functions of government were grouped under these administrative heads, who would serve as the Governors top management team or "secretariats," as they are called now. Governor Linwood Holton's top priority for the 1972 session of the General Assembly was a proposal for a Governor's Cabinet, reorganizing state agencies into six major departments, each headed by a secretary appointed by the governor. Transportation and public safety was one of these six departments. The office of Secretary of Transportation and Public Safety was created on April 8, 1972, by an act passed by the General Assembly. On April 12, 1976, the Legislature established separate secretariats for transportation and for public safety, effective July 1, 1976.
On June 10, 1976, Governor Godwin appointed H. Selwyn Smith, a former Prince William County commonwealth's attorney (1960-1968) and former state senator (1972-1975), as the first Secretary of Public Safety. Smith was reappointed by Governor-elect John N. Dalton in December 1977, and resigned effective July 1, 1980 after he was appointed judge of the 31st Judicial Circuit of Virginia. Governor Dalton named T. Rodman Layman, an Alcoholic Beverage and Control Board Commissioner (1970-1980), to succeed Smith as Secretary of Public Safety. Layman served until the end of Governor Dalton's term in January 1982.
Scope and Content
Contains correspondence, subject files and reports created and collected by the Virginia Office of the Secretary of Public Safety. The files relate mostly to the agencies and boards that were under the Secretary's supervision. Files in this collection document many of the activities of the Department of Corrections, the Department of Criminal Justice Services, the Virginia State Police and the Department of Alcoholic Beverage Control. Files pertaining to a variety of smaller agencies, boards, and committees related to public safety are also included.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into the following series:
Series I. Correspondence and Subject files, 1976-1982
Series II. Reports, 1980-1981
Contents List
- Series I. Correspondence and Subject Files, 1976-1982., Extent: 5 cubic feet (5 boxes). (Box 1-5)
  Contains correspondence and subject files pertaining to a variety of public safety issues, as well as to the activities of the agencies and boards under the heading of the Virginia Office of the Secretary of Public Safety. The correspondence and subject files are broken down into two subgroups: General Files, which are mostly subject files, and State Agency and Committee Files, which document the Secretary's involvement with public safety agencies, boards and committees.
  Arranged alphabetically by folder title.
  - General Files.
    - Boy's State, 1977-1981. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Car Report, 1978-1981. (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Coal Conversion, 1978-1980. (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Code Commission, 1980-1981. (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Comptroller, Office of the, 1978-1980. (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Crime Prevention, 1980-1981. (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Crime Prevention, 1981. (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Emergency Services, Office of, 1976-1980. (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Energy Conservation, 1979-1980. (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Engineering and Building, Division of, 1980-1981. (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Federal Regulations, 1981. (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - General Services, 1977-1981. (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Governor (Dalton), 1981-1982. (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Handicapped Children, 1979-1981. (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Intergovernmental Affairs, 1979-1980. (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Invoices, 1981. (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Legislation (General), 1980-1981. (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Management Analysis and System Development (MASD), 1978-1982. (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Offender Aid and Restoration (OAR), 1981. (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Office Space Questionaire, 1980-1981. (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Personnel, 1981. (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Planning and Budget, Department of, 1978-1981. (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Police Association (Chiefs), 1976-1981. (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - State Property, 1981. (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - State Property (Department of Motor Vehicles), 1977-1981. (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Retirement System, 1979-1981. (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Retrocession (Blue Ridge Parkway), 1979-1981. (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Slayton's Subcommittee (Corrections System), 1980-1981. (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - United Way, 1980-1981. (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Virginia Executive Development Institute, 1981. (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Vocational Education, Virginia State Advisory Council on, 1980-1981. (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - State Agency and Committee Files.
    - Alcoholic Beverage Control, Department of, 1981. (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Capitol Police, 1980-1982. (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Committee on Correctional Overcrowding (Ad Hoc), 1980-1981. (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Commonwealth's Attorneys Services and Training Council, 1980-1981. (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Corrections, Department of, (Correctional Enterprises), 1977-1981. (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Corrections, Department of, (Correspondence), 1981. (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Corrections, Department of, (Employee Complaints), 1979-1981. (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Corrections, Department of, (Fire Marshal), 1980-1981. (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Corrections, Department of, (Inmate Correspondence), 1981-1982. (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Corrections, Department of, (Insiders Program), 1979-1981. (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Corrections, Department of, (Juvenile Justice System), 1980-1981. (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Corrections, Department of, (Mecklenburg Correctional Center), 1979-1981. (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Corrections, Department of, (Medical), 1978-1981. (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Corrections, Department of, (Ombudsman), 1980-1981. (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Corrections, Department of, (Overcrowding), 1981. (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Corrections, Department of, (Pardons), 1978-1979. (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Corrections, Department of, (Parole Board), 1978-1981. (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Corrections, Department of, (Philosophy of Corrections), 1976. (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Corrections, Department of, (Population), 1979-1981. (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Corrections, Department of, (Powhatan Correctional Center), 1981. (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Corrections, Department of, (Prison Construction), 1981. (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Corrections, Department of, (Records Procedures), undated. (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - Corrections, Department of, (Reimbursement to Localities), 1981. (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - Corrections, Department of, (Reorganization), 1978-1980. (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - Corrections, Department of, (Rights of the Institutionalized), 1981. (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - Corrections, Department of, (Sentence Reductions), 1981. (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - Corrections, Department of, (Sentencing Alternatives), 1981. (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - Corrections, Department of, (Southampton Correctional Center), 1976-1981. (Box 4, Folder 22)
    - Corrections, Department of, (Southwestern State Hospital), 1979-1981. (Box 4, Folder 23)
    - Corrections, Department of, (Transfer of Prisoners by Treaties), 1980-1981. (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Corrections, Department of, (Youth and Community Services Division), 1979-1981. (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Council on Criminal Justice, 1980-1981. (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Criminal Justice Services Commission, 1981. (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Criminal Justice Services, Department of, 1981. (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Fire Services Commission, 1981. (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Justice and Crime Prevention, Division of, (Organization and Management Review), 1976-1978. (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Juvenile Justice and Delinquency Prevention Advisory Council, 1981. (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Rehabilitative School Authority, (Correspondence), 1981. (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - State Police Association, 1976-1980. (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - State Police, Department of, (Coal Strike), 1981. (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - State Police, Department of, (Emissions Inspection Program), 1981. (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - State Police, Department of, (General Correspondence), 1981. (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - State Police, Department of, (Investigations), 1981. (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - State Police, Department of, (Nonresident Violator Compact), 1979-1981. (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - State Police, Department of, (Radar Detection Devices), 1977-1981. (Box 5, Folder 16)
    - State Police, Department of, (State-Wide Interdepartmental Radio System), 1979-1981. (Box 5, Folder 17)
    - State Police, Department of, (Reorganization, 7th Division), 1978-1981. (Box 5, Folder 18)
    - State Police, Department of, (Uniforms), 1978-1981. (Box 5, Folder 19)
    - Subcommittee on Prison Industries and Work Release, 1980. (Box 5, Folder 20)
- Series II. Reports, 1980-1981., Extent: 1 cubic foot (1 box). (Box 6)
  Contains a variety of reports, mostly related to the Department of Corrections, its programs and budget.
  Arranged alphabetically by title or agency name.
  - Correctional Industries Sales/Employment Survey, 1981. (Box 6)
  - Corrections, Department of, (Adults and Children under Community Supervision, FY 1980), 1981. (Box 6)
  - Corrections, Department of, (Aerial Photographs of Correctional Facilities), undated, circa 1970. (Box 6)
  - Corrections, Department of, (Children Committed, FY 1981), 1981. (Box 6)
  - Corrections, Department of, (Financial Exhibit Addendum, FY 1982-1984), 1981. (Box 6)
  - Corrections, Department of, (Program Exhibit, Adult Institutions, FY 1982-1984), 1981. (Box 6)
  - Corrections, Department of, (Program Exhibit, Boards and Divisions, FY 1982-1984), 1981. (Box 6)
  - Corrections, Department of, (Program Exhibit, Correctional Enterprises, FY 1982-1984), 1981. (Box 6)
  - Corrections, Department of, (Program Exhibit, Executive Summary, FY 1982-1984), 1981. (Box 6)
  - Corrections, Department of, (Program Exhibit, Grants and Reimbursements to Localities, FY 1982-1984), 1981. (Box 6)
  - Corrections, Department of, (Program Exhibit, Juvenile Learning Centers, FY 1982-1984), 1981. (Box 6)
  - Justice and Crime Prevention, Division of, (Juveniles in Jail in Virginia: An Assessment of the Impact of Removing Juveniles from Local Jails), 1981. (Box 6)
  - Wilderness/Adventure Programs for Juvenile Offenders, 1980. (Box 6)